Academic Departments - Record Group 9 WLU.RG.0009
Washington and Lee University, James G. Leyburn Library Special Collections and Archives
Academic Departments - Record Group 9
Date Not Yet Determined
Washington and Lee University, James G. Leyburn Library Special Collections and Archives
Washington and Lee University
WLU.RG.0009
x Linear Feet
Scope and Contents
This record group contains materials created by individual academic departments.
Existence and Location of Copies
View materials from this collection online via W&L's Digital Archive
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research use.
- Department of Accounting
- Art and Art History Department
  - Staniar Gallery
    - Vincent Valdez: The Strangest Fruit, 2015
      Scope and Contents
      Booklet for the exhibit The strangest Fruit by Vincent Valdez, which was on display in Staniar Gallery from April 27-May 29, 2015. It includes essays by various scholars about the widespread, institutionalized racism experienced by many of color in America.
  - Fine Arts Washington and Lee University
    Washington and Lee University. Art Department
    - Brochure
    - Prof. Lee Kahn and Troubadour Theatre, 1981-08-10-1981-08-24; 2 Item
      Washington and Lee University. Art Department; Kahn, Lee
- Biology Department
- Department of Business Administration
- Chemistry and Biochemistry Department
- Classics Department
- Computer Science Department
- East Asian Languages and Literatures Program
  - East Asian Studies brochure, 1977
  - East Asian Studies Newsletter, 1990-2004; 14 Item
- Department of Economics
- English Department
  - Instructions for Long Theme in English, 1937-1938
  - 25 Student Essays, 1961; 2 Item
    These essays, written by freshmen and sophmores, were compiled and edited by members of the Department of English to serve as examples of both good and bad writing to other students.
- Environmental Studies Department
- Department of Geology
  - Geologic Cross Section of Highland County, VA, 1877; Ruffner, William Henry
  - Summer Institute in Geology for Secondary School Science Teachers, 1966-1967
- German and Russian Department
- Department of History
  - Depart of History, Transcript of Exit Interviews, 1997; Ashworth, Jennifer; .4 Linear Feet
    Transcript includes exit interviews with forty graduating African American students at Washington and Lee University in 1997 conducted by Jennifer Ashworth, the administrative assistant in the History Department.
  - History Department Assessment, 1997; Washington and Lee University; McAhren, Robert W. (Robert Willard)
    Immediate Source of Acquisition
    Gift of Professor Ted Delaney, Septmenber 2,2015. This is an assessment of the History Department based on a survey given to students.
  - History 269, Prof. Ted DeLaney, Washington and Lee University Spring Term Class Postings from two college Civil Rights Classes on a tour of the South., 2015-05-01-2015-05-11-2016-04-30-2016-05-08; Delaney, Theodore C., Jr., Dr.; 1 Files
    African Americans. Civil Rights
    - The First Freedom Ride: Journey of Reconciliation, 1947, 2015-05-01; Church, Cory; 1 Item
    - Voting Rights Movement in Selma, Alabama, 2015-05-01; Riley, Megan; 2 Item
    - Violent Action in Lowndes Country and the Deep South States, 2015-05-01; Honig, Batsheva; 3 Item
    - The Media and the Freedom Riders, 2015-05-02; Merchant, Miller; 4 Item
    - The Present in the Past, 2015-05-04; Longrod, Liz; 5 Item
    - Who says you can't go home?, 2015-05-04; Church, Cory; 6 Item
    - Freedom Ride: Drawbacks and Concerns that were Overlooked, 2015-05-04; Vinneau-Hathaway, Janelle; 7 Item
    - Diversity within the Movement for Racial Equality, 2015-05-04; Honig, Batsheva; 8 Item
    - Sheyann Webb and Rachel West Nelson, 2015-05-04; Swatski, Samantha; 9 Item
    - The Greensboro Sit-Ins, 2015-05-05; Riley, Megan; 12 Item
    - Selma, 2015-05-06; Merchant, Miller; 13 Item
    - "How long? Not Long", 2015-05-07; Swatski, Samantha; 14 Item
    - From Revolution to Reconciliation?, 2015-05-07; Church, Cory; 15 Item
    - History of Regular People, 2015-05-07; Longrod, Liz; 16 Item
    - No Safe Place, 2015-05-07; Honig, Batsheva; 17 Item
    - The Church Bombing, 2015-05-08; Riley, Megan; 18 Item
    - The Ongoing Question of Discrimination, 2015-05-08; Merchant, Miller; 19 Item
    - The March Continues, 2015-05-09; Church, Cory; 20 Item
    - Medgar Evers House, 2015-05-11; Swatski, Samantha; 21 Item
    - The Tragedy of a Forgotten Past, 2015-05-11; Honig, Batsheva; 22 Item
    - Medgar Evers and the Rights Movement, 2015-05-11; Merchant, Miller; 23 Item
    - From Emmett Till to Tamir Rice: Black Boys, Racial Violence, and the Media, 2015-05-11; Longrod, Liz; 24 Item
    - Justice for 16th Street Baptist Church, 2016-04-30; Bravi, Trichia; 25 Item
    - "this is not a method for cowards....", 2016-04-30; Jones, Jamaal; 26 Item
    - Properly Honoring the Legacy of Dr. King, 2016-04-30; Gray, Maggie; 27 Item
    - The Sixteenth Street Baptist Church and the Civil Rights Movement, 2016-04-30; Ries, Riley; 28 Item
    - Jim Crow and the Struggle for Freedom, 2016-05-08; Dunn, Marquita; 29 Item
    - Tracking Hate, 2016-05-08; Bravi, Trichia; 30 Item
    - New Orleans's Lower Ninth Ward, 2016-05-08; Dunn, Marquita; 31 Item
    - The Children of the Movement, 2016-05-08; Gray, Maggie; 32 Item
    - The Murder of Emmett Till, 2016-05-08; Ries, Riley; 33 Item
    - "We Shall Overcome", 2016-05-06; Jones, Jamaal; 34 Item
    - The Ongoing Fight for Civil Rights, 2016-05-06; Ries, Riley; 35 Item
- Mathematics Department
- Journalism Department
  - Journalism Laboratory Press Publications
    - Publications, 1932-1934; 20 Item (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Zeta Deuteron Chapter of Phi Gamma Delta, 1933; Washington and Lee University. Journalism Laboratory Press; 4 Item
        This folder describes the history of The Zeta Deuteron Chapter of Phi Gamma Delta fraternity.
        Fraternal organizations
      - Winter Sports Washington and Lee University, 1933; Washington and Lee University. Journalism Laboratory Press; Washington and Lee University. Department of Athletics; 2 Item
        A card listing all sports at W & L for winter 1933-34.
        Winter sports
      - Annals of Pi, 1933; Washington and Lee University. Journalism Laboratory Press
        This booklet describes the activities of the Pi Chapter of Pi Kappa Alpha fraternity during for the 1932-33 school year.
      - A Look Back, 1934; Washington and Lee University. Journalism Laboratory Press; Lauck, Charles Harold; 2 Volumes
        This booklet is an address delivered before the Eleventh Annual Conference on Printing Education. It describes the Vollbehr Collection in the Library of Congress.
        Incunabula; Incunabula -- Collectors and collecting; Incunabula -- Library resources; Printing in education
      - In Praise of Print, 1934; Washington and Lee University. Journalism Laboratory Press; Lauck, Charles Harold
        This booklet contains a description of the then new rare book room of the Library of Congress.
        Rare books
      - Lee: The Background of a Great Decision. August 1865, 1934; Washington and Lee University. Journalism Laboratory Press; Lee Memorial Association; Gaines, Francis Pendleton
        An address by President Gaines to the officers and directors of The Robert E. Lee Memorial Foundation.
        Speeches, addresses, etc., American; Virginia; Washington and Lee University; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward)
      - These Are the Dreams, 1935; Washington and Lee University. Journalism Laboratory Press; Washington and Lee University; Lauck, Charles Harold
        A collection of poems by Joe H.Ford, Jr., a student who died prematurely at age 18 while attending W & L. Illustrated.
        Poets; Poetry
      - 1932 Football Schedule, Washington and Lee University. Journalism Laboratory Press; Washington and Lee University. Department of Athletics. Football; 2 Item
        College athletes
      - Annals of Pi. Alumni edition., 1934; Washington and Lee University. Journalism Laboratory Press; 4 Item
        This booklet describes the activities of the Pi Chapter of Pi Kappa Alpha fraternity during the 1933-34 school year.
      - Generals Fiji, 1934; Washington and Lee University. Journalism Laboratory Press; 2 Item
        This booklet describes the activities of The Zeta Deuteron Chapter of Phi Gamma Delta fraternity during the 1933-34 school year.
    - Publications, 1935; 8 Item (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Constitution and By-Laws of Washington and Lee Chapter of Delta Upsilon, 1935; Washington and Lee University. Journalism Laboratory Press; 2 Item
        This folder lists the constitution and by-laws of Delta Upsilon.
      - The Beginnings of Printing in Virginia, 1935; Washington and Lee University. Journalism Laboratory Press; Washington and Lee University; Lauck, Charles Harold
        There are three one-page advertisemnts announcing the publication of the above title.
        Printing -- Historiography; Printing presses; Virginia -- Williamsburg
      - The Teacher and the School Publication, 1935; Washington and Lee University. Journalism Laboratory Press
        This folder is a brief paper read before the Fourteenth Annual Conference on Printing Education.
        Student publications
      - Annals of Pi, 1935; Washington and Lee University. Journalism Laboratory Press; 2 Item
        This booklet describes the activities of the Pi Chapter of Pi Kappa Alpha fraternity during the 1934-35 school year.
      - The National Graphic Arts Education Guild, 1935; Washington and Lee University. Journalism Laboratory Press; Washington and Lee University; Lauck, Charles Harold
        The organization,its constitution and its bylaws.
        Graphic arts
    - Publications, 1936; 5 Item (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Friends of Education .Washington and Lee University Bulletin. Vol 35 No 3 Feb.20,1936, Washington and Lee University. Journalism Laboratory Press; Washington and Lee University; 2 Item
        In this booklet, President Gaines recognizes notable contributors to the university.
        College benefactors
      - Philobilon Eine Zeitschrift fur Bucherfreunde Vol. 9 No. 5-6 1936 with The First Printing in Virginia inserted, Washington and Lee University. Journalism Laboratory Press; McMurtrie, Douglas C. (Douglas Crawford); Philobiblon. A Magazine for Book Collectors; Herbert Reichner Verlag; Lauck, Charles Harold
        This German journal has The First Printing in Virginia by Douglas C. McMurtie tipped into the center of the volume. The back of the insert says 'Designed, composed in Linotype Baskerville, and printed by C. Harold Lauck at the Journalism Laboratory Press of Washington and Lee University, Lexington, Virginia, U. S. A., for Philobiblon, a Book-Collector's Magazine published by Herbert Reicher, Vienna, Austria. December 1935'
        Book collecting -- Periodicals; German periodicals; Printing; Printing industry; Virginia; Virginia -- Williamsburg; Virginia -- Jamestown
    - Publications, 1936; 9 Item (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Friends of Education, 1936; Washington and Lee University. Journalism Laboratory Press; Lauck, Charles Harold; Gaines, Francis Pendleton; Junkin, Marion Montague
        This book is a tribute to the many benefactors of Washington and Lee. Drawings by Marion Junkin.
        Educational benefactors; Education, Higher; Virginia -- Lexington; Gaines, Francis Pendleton
      - Washington and Lee University bulletin Vol.35 No.3, 1936; Washington and Lee University. Journalism Laboratory Press; Lauck, Charles Harold; Gaines, Francis Pendleton; Junkin, Marion Montague
        This book is a tribute to the many benfactors of Washington and Lee. Its is a special issue of the Washington and Lee University Bulletin. Drawings by Marion Junkin.
      - Phi Beta Kappa, 1936; Washington and Lee University. Journalism Laboratory Press; Washington and Lee University. Phi Beta Kappa; Washington and Lee University. Phi Kappa Psi; 2 Item
        This book coantains a brief history of The Gamma of Virginia Chapter ,the constitution and by-laws, and a list of Phi Beta Kappa members from 1911-1936.
        Academic achievement
      - Eugene Cole Powell, 1840-1920, 1935; Washington and Lee University. Journalism Laboratory Press; Lauck, Charles Harold
        An address, delivered on the occasion of the presentation of a portrait of Dr. Powell to Dinwiddie County, Va., by his grandson, Dr.Richard Powell Carter, class of 1959.
        Virginia -- Dinwiddie County; Family -- Portraits; Surgeons; Military campaigns; Confederate States of America. Army. Virginia Cavalry Regiment, 3rd; Powell, Eugene Cole
      - Year Book of the Garden Club of Virginia, 1935-1936; Washington and Lee University. Journalism Laboratory Press; Garden Club of Virginia; 2 Item
        This booklet contains the group's bylaws, list of member clubs by city and county, list of committee members,and list of previous awardees.
        Flower gardening -- Societies, etc.
    - Publications, 1937-1938; 4 Item (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - White Columns, 1938-09-01; Washington and Lee University. Journalism Laboratory Press; Lauck, Charles Harold; 4 Volumes
        American poetry; Poets
      - Two Lectures by Americo Castro, 1948; Washington and Lee University. Journalism Laboratory Press; 2 Item
        Folder. An announcement of lectures by ProfessorAmericao Castro, Don Quixote and Litertaure and Human Values.
        Romance languages; Fantasy literature, Spanish
      - An Appraisal of Graphic Arts Education, 1938; Washington and Lee University. Journalism Laboratory Press; Lauck, Charles Harold; 2 Volumes
        "An informal Evaluation of the Several Educational Activities in Terms of Their Contributions to the Graphic Industries."
        Graphic arts; Graphic arts -- Technological innovations; Graphic arts -- Management; Printing
      - Washington and Lee: Progress and Needs. Washington and Lee University Bulletin Vol 37 No 1, 1938; Washington and Lee University. Journalism Laboratory Press; Washington and Lee University
        An informal report to the alumni by the president.
      - Southern Newspaper Publishers' Association, 1903-1936; Washington and Lee University. Journalism Laboratory Press; Lauck, Charles Harold
        This booklet contains information about the group's officers. It was distributed at the group's 34th annual convention in Asheville,NC, May 18,19 and 20, 1936.
        Press; Newspapers
      - Fourth Annual Graphic Arts Education Guild Yearbook, 1939; Graphic Arts Education Guild; Washington and Lee University. Journalism Laboratory Press
        This book contains a Who's Who of members and a brief summary of the guild's yearly activities.
        Graphic arts; Societies
      - Type Revivals, 1937; Washington and Lee University. Journalism Laboratory Press; Washington and Lee University; Lauck, Charles Harold; 1 Box
        This booklet describes independent type designs.
      - Third Annual Graphic Arts Education Guild Yearbook, 1938; Washington and Lee University. Journalism Laboratory Press; Graphic Arts Education Guild
        This book contains a Who's Who of officers and members as well a brief summation of the guild's yearly activities.
      - Year Book of The Garden Club of Virginia, 1936-1937; Washington and Lee University. Journalism Laboratory Press; Garden Club of Virginia
        This booklet contains the group's bylaws, list of member clubs by county and city, list of committee members, and list of previous awardees.
      - Graphic Arts Education Guild Yearbook, 1937; Graphic Arts Education Guild; Washington and Lee University. Journalism Laboratory Press
        This book contains a Who's Who of members in addition to a summary of the guild's yearly activities.
      - An Appraisal of Graphic Arts Education, 06-01-1938; Washington and Lee University. Journalism Laboratory Press; Lauck, Charles Harold
        This booklet presents a critical look at the the state of graphics arts education by on of its early leading proponents, Harry L. Gage.
        Graphic arts; Linotype
    - Publications, 1939; 3 Item (Box 2, Folder 6)
      - The William Parks Paper Mill at Wiiliamsburg, 1939; Washington and Lee University. Journalism Laboratory Press
        A paper read before the Bibliographical Society of America describing the first and oldest paper mill in colonial Virginia. R
        Paper mills
      - Scenic and Historic Map of Lexington and Environs, 1939; Washington and Lee University. Journalism Laboratory Press
        A map showing Lexington and the surrounding countryside sent to alumni at Christmas 1939.sent out
        Virginia -- Lexington
    - Publications, 1940-1943; 17 Item (Box 2, Folder 7)
      - The Lee Memorial Journalism Foundation, 09-01-1942; Washington and Lee University. Journalism Laboratory Press; Lauck, Charles Harold; 3 Item (Box 2, Folder 8, Box data_value_missing_85bb78d36d1e5305032e1e2553be086b)
        This book is a physical history of the Lee Memorial Journalism Foundation written by C. Tom Garten '42 ass part of a research project. It describes the origins and growth of the foundation up to the early 1940's.
        Journalism, College -- Study and teaching; Washington and Lee University. Journalism Department
      - The Zeta Sig, 1942; Washington and Lee University. Journalism Laboratory Press; 2 Item
        This booklet describes the activities of The Zeta Chapter of Sigma Chi fraternity for the 1941-42 school year.
      - Annals of Pi, 1941; Washington and Lee University. Journalism Laboratory Press; 2 Item
        This booklet describes the activities of the Pi Chapter of Pi Kappa Alpha fraternity during the 1940-41 school year.
      - Marching Along in Beta Theta Pi, 1942; Washington and Lee University. Journalism Laboratory Press; 2 Item
        This booklet describes the activities of the Alpha Ro Chapter of Beta Theta Pi fraternity during the 1941-42 school year.
      - Marching Along in Beta Theta Pi, 1941; Washington and Lee University. Journalism Laboratory Press; 2 Item
        This booklet describes the activities of the Alpha Ro Chapter of Beta Theta Pi during the 1940-412 school yesr.
      - Washington and Lee University Commencement Day, 1940; Washington and Lee University. Journalism Laboratory Press; 2 Item
        The commencement program for June 7, 1940.
        Commencement ceremonies
      - Imprimatur, 1943; Washington and Lee University. Journalism Laboratory Press; Lauck, Charles Harold; 2 Item
        'A folio of personalities,impressions and observations...'.A kekepsake issue of a newsletter edited by Lloyd Emerson Siberell.
        Critics -- Books and reading; Book collecting
      - The Washington Literary Society, 1940; Washington and Lee University. Journalism Laboratory Press
        Related Materials
        This folder gives a brief historical sketch of the Washington Literary Society.
        Literary movements; Writing
      - The Caduciette, 1941; Washington and Lee University. Journalism Laboratory Press; 2 Item
        This booklet describes the activities of The Mu Chapter of Kappa Sigma fraternity during the 1940-41 school year.
      - Mrs. George Junkin Irwin, Violinist, 1940; Washington and Lee University. Journalism Laboratory Press; 3 Item
        A program for a violin concert by Mrs. George Junkin (Ruby Johnson) Irwin.
        Women violinists; Concerts
      - The School for Special Service, 1943; Washington and Lee University. Journalism Laboratory Press
        This folder describes the U.S. Army's School for Special Service, the Eighth Class of which was held at Washington and Lee.
        Basic training (Military education); Military education; World War (1939-1945)
      - Washington and Lee University Bulletin. Vol. 42 No. 5., 1943; 2 Item
        This copy of the W&L Bulletin is a message to alumni discussing the univrsity's commitment to preparing students for military service. Includes a list of casualties, POW's and MIA's.
        World War (1939-1945); Military education; Washington and Lee University. Journalism Laboratory Press
      - News Letter. Washington and Lee University Bulletin. Vol.42 No.6, 1943; Washington and Lee University. Journalism Laboratory Press; Lauck, Charles Harold; Latture, Rupert Nelson; 2 Item
        This edition of the Washington and Lee University Bulletin is a Christmas issue prepared for students who had joined the armed forces.
        Soliders; World War (1939-1945)
      - Graphic Arts Education in Wartime, 08-01-1942; Washington and Lee University. Journalism Laboratory Press; Lauck, Charles Harold
        This booklet contains the entire annual report of the National Graphic Arts Education Association. It was written by Fred. J. Hartman.
      - The First Five Years of the National Graphic Arts Education Guild, 1935-1940, 06-01-1940; Washington and Lee University. Journalism Laboratory Press; Lauck, Charles Harold
        This booklet is a report outlining the progress of the early years of the National Graphic Arts Education Guild.
        Graphic arts; Printing in education
      - Fifty Books of the Year, 1941; Washington and Lee University
        This four page pamphlet describes an exhibition of American bookmaking and graarphic arts in McCormick Library
    - Publications, 1944-1949; 26 Item (Box 2, Folder 9, Box data_value_missing_f564cdfb267f4be77ed40b207765f6d9)
      - Washington and Lee University Commencement Day, 1948; Washington and Lee University. Journalism Laboratory Press
        The commencement program for June 4, 1948.
      - The Blue Ridge Garden Club Presents Trial by Jury, 1944; Washington and Lee University. Journalism Laboratory Press; Lauck, Charles Harold; 2 Item
        This is the program for the Gibert and Sullivan play 'Trial by Jury'. Theis play was actually performed in the Rockbridge County Court House.
        Detective and mystery plays; Detective and mystery plays, English
      - Washington and Lee University Bulletin. Vol.46 No.9, 1947; Washington and Lee University. Journalism Laboratory Press; Gaines, Francis Pendleton; 2 Item
        Scholarships; Fund raising
      - Washington and Lee and You, 1945; Washington and Lee University. Journalism Laboratory Press; Washington and Lee University. Alumni Office; 2 Item
        This one page folder seeks contributions from alumni.alumni for contributions.
        Fund raising
      - Washington and Lee Alumni Fund. Why... Wherefore...Whither., 1947; Washington and Lee University. Journalism Laboratory Press; 2 Item
        This small folder seeks contributions froorm alumni.
      - Washington and Lee University Bulletin. Vol.43 No.1, 1944; Washington and Lee University. Journalism Laboratory Press
        This issue of the University Bulletin addresses 1940's choices for students - education or military service.
        Students and war; Veterans -- Education
      - Washington and Lee University Bulletin. Vol.45 No.2, 1946; Washington and Lee University. Journalism Laboratory Press
        This issue of the University Bulletin provides general information about classes and university services available to returning veterans.
        Veterans; Veterans -- Education
      - Washington and Lee 1947 Football Season, Washington and Lee University. Journalism Laboratory Press; Washington and Lee University. Department of Athletics; 2 Megabytes
        This brochure provides ticket information and the schedule for the 1947 football season. and the schedule.
        Athletics
      - Washington and Lee 1948 Football Season, Washington and Lee University. Journalism Laboratory Press; Washington and Lee University. Department of Athletics. Football
        This brochure includes ticket information and the 1948 schedule. Two brochures togeteher, never cut apart.